Okay, welcome back to Garys Economics.
Today, we are going to explain the only way
to stop the far right from taking power in your country.
Okay, I'm filming this on Tuesday the 12th of May.
This will go out on Sunday the 17th of May.
We have had,
in the last week, local elections up and down the UK.
The Labour Party, our governing party, got smashed.
They lost an enormous amount of seats.
A big chunk on their left to the Greens,
but a much bigger chunk on their right to Reform,
our far-right party.
It was a bit of a disaster for Labour.
As
I'm filming this, Keir Starmer is fighting for his life.
He could be out even by the time
this video goes out, or he could have resigned.
I suspect
he will probably last at least a few more months.
We'll see if I'm eating my words by Sunday.
But this is causing a lot of panic
because people are starting to realise the fact
which, to be honest, has been pretty predictable
for a couple of months, and something which I predicted
even a couple of years ago, even before Labour came in,
that the far right are broadly the most popular party
in this country, and if nothing changes,
they are going to win the next election.
And that is not anything
which is at all unique to the UK.
This is happening all across the world.
I was in France last week.
It's happening in Germany.
They're already in power in the US.
They're already in power in Italy.
So today, I'm going to explain to you very simply,
how to stop the far right
from winning power in your country.
And before I start,
I should just mention, because whenever I do
videos like this, I'm always really aware that,
that lots and lots of people, both here in the UK
and across the world, are voting for the far right
and they want the far right to win.
And I really, really don't want this channel to
be a place where people voting for the far right
feel they're not welcome.
So I want to be really, really clear, if you are thinking
about voting for the far right, you're welcome here.
This is not a politically factional channel.
This is about economics.
This is about inequality.
This is about living standards.
I think if the far right get in, it'll be terrible
for inequality, it'll be terrible for living standards.
We're going to put a message
for far right voters at the end, but for now,
we are going to get into the business for those of you
who don't want the far right to win, how can
you stop the far right from winning the next election
here in the UK and in your country as well?
Okay, so I've got a number of things here
which you need to do if you want to stop the far right
from winning in your country.
But to be honest, normally I'd do a big build-up
to the, sort of, the answer in these videos,
but I'm going to come in straightaway
with what I think is number one.
Really, if you come away from this video with anything,
this is the clearest and most simple,
and most important thing which you need to understand
if you want to stop the far right
from winning in your country.
Living standards have been falling, and have fallen
quite a long way for nearly 20 years now, here in the UK
and across the Western world.
You need to recognise that, and you need
to understand that, because that is driving politics,
and that is driving how people think about politics
in a big way.
That has happened in quite an unequal way,
where people towards the top have, in many cases,
seen their living standards improve, but
the vast majority of people, increasingly the bottom 50,
60, 70%, have seen significant deterioration,
especially if they think about future generations
and how their kids will do.
This is driving everything, okay?
At the moment, there is only one political grouping,
political ideology, political group in the world
which is giving a clear and simple message that says,
"We understand your living standards are falling.
We have an answer as to why they are falling, and
we are going to tell you how to fix it." At the moment,
there is only one political group in the world
which is answering that question in a simple way,
and that is the far right.
Now, if I was to go out here on the street now,
today, pull someone to the side
and say, "Listen, what is Labour's answer
to why living standards are falling?
What is the Democrats' answer in the US to
why living standards are falling?" And whatever country
you're watching from, the centre left,
the traditional centre left, centre right parties,
what are their explanations
for why living standards are falling?
I don't think even one in 10 people
would be able to tell you what the answer is.
If you want to understand why the far right are winning
elections across the world, and why the far right
are going to keep winning elections across the world,
it is as simple as this: people are legitimately worried
about falling living standards,
and there is only one group of politicians
here in the UK and across the world
that is providing a clear and simple answer about
why living standards are falling and how to fix it.
As long as that continues, the far right
will keep winning elections across the world.
So how do you change that?
Very, very simply, the other groups of people
in this country and across the world...
And I want to be clear, in the majority of countries,
including this country, a decent majority of the public
don't want the far right to win.
They are polling first, but on sort of 26,
27% of the vote, which is, like, not a...
Which is a minority.
The other group of people in the country,
if you want to stop the far right from winning,
you need to coalesce on a clear and simple message
on the economy, on living standards, on
how you are going to stop living standards from falling.
It is as simple as that.
And I'm going to make a pitch to you here and now.
If your message on how
you're going to stop living standards from falling, and
on how you understand that living standards are falling,
is not about inequality, is not about billionaires,
is not about taxing the richest people in society, is
not about tax wealth, not work, then be honest with me.
What the **** is it? Seriously,
If that is not going to be the message that the left
and the centre coalesce around on the economy
and living standards, what is your message going to be?
Because I've been following politics and politicians
for many, many years in this country
and in other countries,
and they seem to have been trying to sell a message
which is about productivity and about growth
and about efficiency and about investment,
and that obviously sounds fantastic
to people with economics degrees.
But people in the street, the general public,
have heard this exact message on the economy
from political parties and politicians
on the centre-left and on the centre-right again
and again and again for the last 20 years.
And every single time they have voted in a politician
that is doing this kind of economics,
techno babble, efficiency, efficiency, growth, growth,
growth, they have seen consistently year after year
after year after year falling living standards,
and they are not going to vote for that again.
So if you want these people to vote for you and
not vote for your opponents who are delivering a simple,
different message on the economy,
you yourself need to have an idea which is not this idea
which the public have clearly seen fail for 20 years.
If it is not inequality, tax the rich, living standards,
what the **** is it?
It has to be tax wealth, not work.
And I've got to put this in the context
of what is currently happening here in the UK.
As I'm saying, I've been engrossed this morning
in seeing whether or not our prime minister will resign.
I think he will survive the week,
but I'm very confident he will not survive...
Well,
I'm increasingly confident he will not survive the year.
Even if he does, we are going to get a new prime minister
here in this country in the next 18 months.
I'm very, very confident of that.
It will probably be much, much sooner than that.
This is a fantastic opportunity for the Labour Party
to come in and signal that they are willing
to do something significantly different on the economy.
And if that new prime minister, whoever he or she is,
be it Burnham or Rayner or Streeting, does not come in
with a message that says, "I am significantly different
to your previous prime minister.
I am significantly different to Starmer.
I'm going to do something significant on the economy,"
then that new prime minister
will become rapidly unpopular just like Starmer did,
as I predicted, just like Sunak did, as I predicted.
All right?
You need to have a message
about how you are different on the economy.
And I'll be clear, I'm here.
You can email us at any point.
I would love to speak to the teams of Streeting
and Rayner and Burnham.
You need to have a pitch on the economy
that says you are different, and we're here to help you.
Okay, so that's the most important thing.
If you take one thing away from this video,
that needs to be it.
You have an opposition that is growing in power,
that has a clear and simple message
on how they're going to stop living standards from falling.
Until you guys coalesce on one message
that is simple and clear and easy to understand
on living standards, you will lose.
Okay, number 2.
The next thing here is...
I've written here...
Probably
should have written this in more formal language.
We need to stop the beef
between the left and the centre.
All right, listen,
I like to think of myself as not politically factional.
All right?
I'm a economic single-issue campaigner.
I campaign on inequality.
I think if we don't deal with inequality, living
standards will keep falling.
I think
that is increasingly being shown to be true by reality.
And I seem to have been,
like, painted by many as the political left.
And in this country and across the world, my ideas
have been much better embraced by the political left
than they have the political centre.
But I think this is a good time
to sort of sit and look at these results.
And I think we have to accept, not just here in the UK,
but across the world, if I'm being totally honest,
in the context of a growing, surging global far right,
I don't think the centre can win without the left.
And if I'm totally honest,
I don't think the left can win without the centre.
I think this is the way that it is.
And I understand there's a lot of
bad blood, and often there's reasons for that,
why people on the left don't like people in the centre.
And I'm sure there's good reasons
why people in the centre don't like people on the left.
The far right will,
will be in control of this country in 3 years unless
we together find some way to work together to stop them.
And I know, not just in this country,
but across the world, the left and the centre
disagree on many, many, many, many things.
Unless we can find one thing that we agree on, which
I think should be living standards, inequality,
the economy, and we get together and fight for it,
then the far right is going to win in this country
and across the world.
And for me, it's quite...
It's frustrating in a way because I actually think,
in many ways, the left offers the exact thing
that the centre needs, and I think it is true that
the centre offers the exact thing that the left needs.
I've been much more
sort of welcomed by the political left in this country
than I have by the political centre in many cases.
Some of the political centre in Labour are
quite hostile to me, whereas obviously the Greens here
and Zach Polanski have... And even before Zach Polanski,
they've really embraced wealth taxes.
But sometimes I worry when I look at the left
that they're not, like, serious and practical
about let's really make sure we win the election.
Let's really make sure
that we, design these taxes correctly.
Let's really make sure that we, dot all the I's
and cross the T's on this and have everything ready.
But then when I look at the centre,
what I see is a group of people
who are, almost like compulsively obsessed
with dotting I's and crossing T's. To the extent
that they will be like almost pathologically unable
to consider even the idea of doing something like
seriously different on the economy.
So you have a group of people who are like
very ideological and really keen to do something
radically different, but don't seem to have that
like ruthless focus on practicality and winning.
And then you have a group of people
who seem only to want to be practical and to win,
but are like totally refusing to consider anything
that seems in any way radically different.
So, we have a big structural problem
in the economy here, and it seems to be only the left
that is willing to accept that.
This is exactly what the centre need...
As I said before, the centre needs a political message
which is clear on the economy, but it absolutely needs
to also be clearly different from Starmerism
and clearly different from Bidenism because
people have seen these like technocratic economics-y
centrist messages fail again and again.
If you want that, the left has that.
But, I think we also have to be realistic.
I'm really proud of,
the work that Zach Polansky has done,
running with the message of the wealth tax,
and they have made massive strides forward electorally
in the last, just one year, and it's amazing.
And, if they think they can continue that,
absolutely good luck to them.
But when I look at the local election results
from last week, we have to be realistic.
I don't think at the moment they're in a situation
where they can win, in places like Wigan,
in places like Sunderland,
in places like much of the north of England.
So I think if you...
If the left want to win, and I'm not saying they,
they don't continue to compete with the centre,
but if the left want to win,
and they don't want the far right to win,
they need to start being open to figuring out some way
that we can work out common ground with the centre.
And if the centre want to win,
and they need to stop collapsing
like they are clearly collapsing, they need to be open
to some of the new ideas being offered by the left.
And it's,
it's incredibly frustrating here, because,
I am not super politically factional.
I don't feel like
really I sit naturally in either of these groups.
But what I see here is 2 groups that,
in theory at least, want to stop inequality
from increasing, sort of tearing each other to pieces,
while the far right, who are funded by billionaires,
in many cases are billionaires themself, have
a literal policy to come in and cut tax on billionaires
and increase inequality are going to win.
Yeah, I'm reminded of the quote from my brother
that I used in a video last year when I asked him,
"How can we stop the far right from winning?"
Where he said very simply, "Relentless
and aggressive pursuit of common ground."
[Jack] And unity.
That's it.
Where he said, "Relentless and aggressive pursuit
of common ground and unity." look, I know that
there's a lot of bad blood between these two groups.
But you're going to have to sit there
and ask yourself, "Do you want the far right
to take control of your country?"
And sometimes achieving important things
is more important than the grievances you may have
with maybe people who did treat you a bit ****
But the fact is I think this is going to be needed,
not just in this country, but across the world.
I was in France last week, and it's the same situation.
If the left and the centre cannot break bread
with each other, then the far right is going to win.
All right, and number 3 is when you are in power,
you can't afford to fail.
So the reason I'm pointing this out is
because my question number one,
my point number one was you need to have a clear message
on the economy on living standards.
But obviously this is like a focus on messaging.
And I get quite frustrated
sometimes when I look at politics.
I sometimes feel like these failing
centrist political parties...
Like when I hear what the people in Labour say
and when I watch like The Rest is Politics,
which is like our main like centrist political podcast
in this country, I kind of feel like that
they constantly think that their problem
is like a comms problem, like a communications problem.
Meanwhile,
what you have is like a bunch of rich guys saying,
"We've got a comms problem" whilst 60%
of the country can't afford to feed their ******* kids,
right?
And it's like, listen, yes, of course,
you need to have a clear message on the economy,
but also, crucially, you need to stop living
standards from falling, which means you need to be ready
to actually take action on the economy.
And I think a massive part of the problem
that Labour have now is that they didn't recognise
before they came in that inequality was a problem.
And the reason why I was able to like
very accurately predict the collapse of Labour and
the collapse of Starmer, I watched that video
before I filmed this video, was because I recognised
that these guys had a massive economic problem
that they were not looking at.
So, the reason I knew that
Starmer would collapse is the same reason that I know
if you get on a boat with a hole in the bottom,
you're going to ******* sink, right?
They were not fixing that problem.
And this brings me to number 4,
which is you need to start doing the prep work now.
It's...
I think sometimes like the,
the conversation about wealth taxes
in this country in particular has moved into a space
which is like really, if I'm honest, quite idiotic.
Where I go and do an interview where I say, "Listen,
growing inequality of wealth is a massive problem.
If you do not deal with that growing inequality of wealth,
you are not in any way going to be able
to stop living standards, not even from not falling,
but from not falling quickly.
Like, you need to deal with this problem."
And then people turn around to me and they say,
"Oh, but if you tax the rich,
they're going to leave." "If you, if you...
You know,
if you look at this wealth tax or that wealth tax,
it was designed badly and it failed." And this...
And then...
I turn around to these people and say, "Okay.
All right.
Fine.
Wealth taxes have in some cases been designed badly.
This is true.
Work with me to design the wealth tax well then."
Listen, if you know there's a hole in the bottom
of your boat, don't turn around to me and say, "Oh,
but last time, my mate Dave,
he had a hole in the bottom of his boat,
and he tried to fix it, and it didn't work."
If somebody once failed to fix, like,
a really serious problem, the solution to that is
to try to fix this problem properly.
I was on Scott Galloway's podcast last week,
and he was pushing me on this.
And, I said to him, "Look,
if you want to find examples of wealth taxes
that are designed badly, you will find them.
And if you want to find examples of planes
that were designed badly and didn't work, you will find
them." Listen, the response to the first guy who tried
to build a plane, building the plane badly,
is not to say, "This is it.
We never build a plane again."
It's to build the plane ******* well.
Listen, last week, I was in France
pushing sort of the new promotion of my book.
But really more than that, I went to France
because I wanted to meet Gabriel Zucman,
who is an inequality economist,
he's been working on this for, 10, 20 years,
who has a team of 35 people there in France
that is working on designing these taxes
so they work well.
And I want to be there so I have a connection to this guy
so that I can get Labour,
who desperately need a new idea, and say,
"Listen, here is the guy that is ****** designing it.
Work with them." Like, I think it's...
We need to move past this, like,
stupidly facile argument where I say, "If you don't
design a good wealth tax, you will die." And people say,
"Oh, well, you ******* show me the wealth tax then." Listen,
I'm a ******* YouTuber out here making a video a week.
The team is there in France, Gabriel Zucman's team.
Listen, if you are Labour
and you're trying to think about what you need to do,
you don't need to talk to me, all right?
I will put you in touch,
or you can go straight to Gabriel Zucman's team.
You need to be looking and talking
to the people in the world who are designing this tax.
Because if you do not get this tax right,
you're going to have the exact same problem that Starmer
has had, or the exact same problem that Rishi Sunak has,
or the exact same problem that Joe Biden had.
Which is you cannot stop living standards from falling
whilst you are presiding over economies
where inequality of wealth is rapidly increasing,
and wealth is being sucked out of the middle class,
and wealth is being sucked out of government.
So these two points come together.
You have to take action when you are in power.
You need to start doing the prep work now.
And I was really happy to meet Zucman,
and we're going to fil- we're going to interview him next week
on the channel.
And if you have any connections with Labour politicians
or the politicians who are in power
or could be in power in your country,
get them to watch next week's video with Gabriel Zucman.
Because I think it's really important that they recognise
this is not just some out-there tax proposal.
This is essential for stopping living standards
from falling, and the people are out there designing it.
You don't have to talk to me if you don't
like me, if you don't like my communication style.
The economists are there that are doing the work.
And if you want to stop the far right from winning,
you need to be speaking to them now.
All right, number 5 is a slight switch of lanes,
but I do think it is incredibly important.
And I've written here social media
with about 10 A's on the end.
Listen, where on earth are the left
and the centre on social media, right?
Like, it's sort of...
It's maddening to me, basically.
I decided
to stop writing for newspapers about 6 years ago now
and shifted to social media because it was obvious
that is where political power is moving.
And if you look at the alt-right, the far right,
whatever you want to call them,
they have a massive social media presence in the US.
And whenever there's, like, a big, like,
young up-and-coming YouTuber anywhere else in the world,
they get funding immediately from these, like,
anonymous, mysterious far-right donors.
And then they get,
they get platformed on things like Joe Rogan,
which is, like, the biggest podcast in the world, right?
And until some other political group,
be they on the left, on the centre,
starts to seriously fund social media and link
up the different influencers across the world together
and platform them on each other's channels,
we're going to keep losing elections.
Because if it's really, really clear
that political power is moving towards social media,
and the only group in the world
that is serious about funding social media,
building that big social media infrastructure
with lots of influencers that know each other
and platform each other on their own platforms.
Until someone else builds that space,
these guys are going to keep winning
because that is so politically powerful.
And I want to add on this, for me personally,
I think the real... the real key here to building
social media influencers that are going
to be really powerful and effective at
moving how the public feel on economics and
on politics is what I call outward-facing social media
that meets the public where they are.
And what by that is, in general, where
I do see good, left social media influencers or...
To be honest, there are almost no good
central social media influencers,
but those that are, what I tend to see is what
I would call inward-facing social media, in the sense of
left-wing influencers that produce content
that is largely designed for a left-wing audience and is
sometimes a little bit demeaning in the way that
it talks about maybe, in this country, Reform voters
or, in the US, Trump voters.
And centrist political media,
a great example in this country
is The Rest is Politics, which talks largely to centrists.
And look, of course,
if you're talking to people like you,
there's going to be a big audience for that kind of thing.
But if you want to be able to convince people
that are not already going to vote the same way as you,
people who in this country might be voting for Reform,
or in the US might be voting for Trump,
or in France might be voting for,
the RN, you need
to be having and funding and supporting influencers
that come from ordinary working class backgrounds
and speak outwards in a compassionate way to the public.
And I have to,
do a big sh- do a big shout-out to the people
who I think are doing a great job of that here.
Louisa Munch, Jimmy the Giant, Barry's Economics.
I think that unless, until and
unless the left and/or the centre build like a serious,
well-funded, outward-facing social media,
you're going to struggle.
You're going to struggle.
And if you are at all involved in left-wing or,
or centrist political funding, you need
to be... you need to be serious about funding this.
And, I'll make a pitch here
to whoever the new Labour leader is.
I'm aware that it could happen
within the next couple of months,
To the teams of Andy Burnham
and Wes Streeting and Angela Rayner and Ed Miliband,
it's almost certainly going to be one of these four.
Listen, none of you have a social media presence, okay?
We are here.
We get millions of views on every month,
We've got,
maybe 4 million subscribers across platforms.
We are the only guys here who can reach the public.
When you come in, you are going to have
to have a pitch about your economy
which says you are different from Starmer,
and you need to sell that to the public.
Listen, if you are s- if you are serious
about not becoming Starmer 2.0, who is basically Rishi
2.0, the next prime minister who immediately
becomes unpopular, you should be talking to us.
Okay, here's the email.
Here's the email.
Message us.
We want to talk to you.
We want to save your economic policy, and we want to
give you a chance to actually communicate to the public.
You have no social media presence.
You should be talking to us.
Here's the email.
All right,
and number 6, you cannot look down on the public.
You cannot look down on the public.
Yeah, I was watching the Rest is Politics last week
in response to these local election results.
And I remember them, they were asking,
"Why is Keir Starmer unpopular?" And,
you have, another prime minister s-
maybe the sixth prime minister in a row
who has presided over a big increase in inequality and
has... and a big decrease in living standards.
And then you have a couple of rich people saying,
"Why is this guy unpopular?"
And this is another thing.
I think when the centre...
What I see with Keir Starmer a lot at the moment,
and also these centrists often do the same thing,
they try to sort of build a parity.
They say, "We're being attacked by populists
on the left and populists on the right."
And they try and say that Reform and Nigel Farage
and Zak Polanski and the Greens are the same.
And whether you believe that or not,
if you sit as a relatively comfortable person
in a country where inequality is increasing quickly,
and you yourself have gotten richer
in the last 10 years, and you turn around to the public
and say, "Why are the public unhappy?" Then
you are, you're desperately out of touch, basically.
And I think you need to recognise that when
you as the centre say both the left and the right are
radicalists or wild and unrealistic,
in a country where the centrist vote is collapsing
and the far right and far left votes are exploding,
the message you send to the public is,
"We do not want to give you change."
And that will kill the political centre,
because the one thing that
the vast majority of the public want here in the UK,
in America,
in France, in Australia, in Italy, in Germany is change.
You cannot dig yourself into a bunker
and say, "No, no, it's the public who are wrong."
And I'm reminded of what I think is probably
the defining political moment really, I think,
of the last 10, 15, 20 years, which was the deplorables
moment from Hillary Clinton.
Let me see if I can get the exact quote.
This was a 2016 quote from Hillary Clinton during the,
the presidential campaign for the first,
Trump's first electoral campaign,
which he won in 2016 against Hillary Clinton,
where she said, "To just be grossly generalistic,
you could put half of Trump's supporters
into what I call the basket of deplorables.
They're racist, sexist, homophobic, xenophobic,
Islamophobic, you name it." and
this was before I was actively involved in politics,
but I remember looking at this and thinking,
"She's lost this election." It's
just as simple as that with one line.
When you hate people, they can feel that you hate them.
And I know what it's like to be a poor person,
growing up in an unequal country
that looks down on poor people.
And I think a big part of this far right vote
is a kind of **** you vote to, like,
a political intellectual intelligentsia class
which kind of hates the public and has left them behind.
And I think...
I got in trouble
for saying something like this last year.
But the truth is, if you respond to a public
which has been left behind and has seen their living
standards fall, especially in a context
where the top 10% has been protected
and the top 5% has massively benefited.
And if you turn around to these people
who are demanding, "Listen, we want something
different" and respond by calling them deplorables
or assuming that they're racist,
then they're going to hate you,
and they're going to vote against you,
and you're going to lose elections.
So listen...
And of course, listen, I'm 100% aware
that racism is increasing in this country.
And of course, it's increasing in the US as well.
And I know that I'm speaking here as a white person who is
not on the end of it, and I know that it's happening.
But the fact is, these guys are going to win the election.
Do you want them to win the election?
And if you don't want them to win the election,
you need to be able to relate to the public
of your country in a compassionate way.
And look,
I'm sitting here in London, and I'm from London.
I'm born and raised in London.
I grew up in a very multicultural, multi-ethnic area.
And the far right, which in this country
is the Reform Party, is not very popular in London,
and they don't get a lot of votes in London.
And it would be really easy for me to turn around
to my audience and say, "Oh yeah, you know, these guys
are a bunch of racists." And I'd probably get
a load of people supporting me on that.
Is that going to win you the election
with people in the north of England
who are considering voting for Reform?
These people have a legitimate right
to demand change, and if you turn around
and call anybody who's demanding change a racist or call
them a deplorable, then they're not going to vote for you.
So I think
this is, like, a really, really important issue here.
It's a really important issue.
Listen, we need to be able to speak to each other
with compassion.
And when people vote for Reform,
I don't ever turn around and blame them.
The way I consider this is I have a public voice here.
If people are voting for Reform,
that's because I didn't make my case well enough.
I will never deliver contempt
to poor people, to weak people.
We need to find ways to work together here.
It's as simple as that, basically.
And that brings me to this number 7,
which is the real big problem
is going to be avoiding this hatred and division,
even in some cases when we are receiving hatred.
It's as simple as this.
I was in France last week
and they kept saying to me,
"Do you think what we need to do is to, like, increase
hatred of billionaires and increase hatred of bankers?
You know, We need a common enemy" this kind of thing.
And what I said to them was,
"I think hatred only feeds the far right.
I think hatred only feeds the far right."
I think if people are hateful and people are angry,
then that feeds the far right in every country.
There's so...
There's a scene in 1984,
George Orwell's great work,
although he's got a lot of great books.
I think it's called the 2 Minutes Hate.
And in this scene, they,
they get everybody, and they sit them in a cinema,
and they show them all these, like, *******
terrible things happening, like horrible things,
and they make you really angry and really angry.
And then when you're really angry, then they flash up
on the screen all the people they want you to hate.
"These are the guys we want you to hate.
These are the guys we want you to hate." And
I think Orwell is a great writer and a great thinker,
and I think that the point he's trying to make
is if you can make people angry, and if you can make
people scared, you can make people hate each other,
then people become easy to manipulate,
and they will become easy to manipulate by the rich,
and the rich who increasingly own the media
and own, in many cases, the political parties.
They are the big funders of Reform
and the far right in basically every country.
If we allow ourselves in this country
and wherever you're watching, to become countries
where ordinary poor people, working class people
hate each other, cannot talk to each other,
cannot look each other in the eye,
then I think the far right will win.
And we need to avoid that.
We need to avoid that wherever we are.
And you need to be able to ask yourself,
if you're watching from London
or if you're watching from, New York,
or a big city where you have a degree
and you're educated, ask yourself,
what must it feel like to be somebody
who doesn't have a university degree, who's growing up
in some left-behind part of the country,
who's growing up in Sunderland, or who's growing up
in Grimsby or in Blackpool or,
parts of the South or parts of the Midwest where
they're, where they're separated from these big centers.
And we need to be able to be compassionate
and find that common ground.
If we cannot find that common ground,
we're going to keep losing.
And you know, I...
This brings me back to my first point,
basically, which is...
Well, it's my second point, actually.
I look at
the votes last week, and again, massive congratulations
to the work that Zack and the Greens have done.
But I'm not sure the Greens can win in Sunderland,
and parts
of the Midlands and parts of the North.
Which means we need to be looking at each other
and figuring out how can we work together,
what is our common ground,
and crucially, what is our shared common message
on living standards that we deliver to the public.
If we do not have a shared, simple,
common message on the economy, on living standards that
we deliver to the public together, then we will lose.
And lastly, I promised
I would do a message to Reform voters
and people who are considering voting Reform
because I honestly mean it.
Like, you know, this is not a space... this is not
a space just for Green voters or just for Labour voters.
Like, I am not politically factional.
I'm trying to get action on inequality,
and everyone is welcome here.
Everybody is welcome here,
regardless of who you vote for.
And I recognise that
a lot of the people who are voting for Reform
are poor people from up and down this country.
And I grew up poor, and I know what it's like
to be a poor person and to be looked down on
and to feel like there's this group of people
who don't give a **** about you and are ignoring you.
And I just want to say, look, I know what
it's like, and I recognise why it is.
And the reason I'm here is because I'm trying to stop
your living standards from falling.
I understand
that it's difficult for young people to buy houses,
to have families, to get financial security.
That is the reason I'm here.
And I know you are ****** off
with Keir Starmer and with Labour, and to be honest,
I'm pretty ****** off as well.
And I know maybe some of you don't trust,
Zack Polanski and the Greens,
and it's on them to try and convince you. But what
I need to tell you is be careful who you trust.
Because when I look at that Reform Party,
and when I look at Nigel Farage, what I see is a party
run by rich people, funded by rich people,
with a policy to immediately cut taxes
on the richest people in our society,
which is going to increase living standards...
When I look at Reform, when I look at Farage,
what I see is a party run by rich people,
funded by very rich people, that have a policy as soon
as they come in to cut taxes on the richest people
in our society, which is going to increase inequality
and decrease living standards for you.
And look, I know that maybe when you look at them,
you think, "Well, look, there's nobody else who's,
who's with me, who's on my side." Help us to build it.
Help us to build it.
Listen,
I have been floating around the London political class
for, 10 years now,
the last 2 or 3 years quite closely.
And listen,
in many cases, I find it incredibly frustrating.
And,
I'm often as pissed off with them as you are.
But listen, look at what's happening in America.
Look at what's happening in Italy.
Look at what happened in Poland and Hungary.
In the countries where these guys got voted in,
they cut taxes on the rich, they increased inequality,
and it didn't do anything.
It made living standards worse
for ordinary working people.
And you know what?
Very often I want to stick my finger
in the eye of the elites just as much as you do, but
that's not going to help you and it's not going to help me.
So listen, help me build something here.
Help me build something.
Listen, I want to force these political parties to move.
I want them to...
I want to force them to move to a situation
where they prioritise the living standards
of ordinary working people like you.
I get up every day
and I'm talking to all these people, and right now,
as we're in the midst of trying to
get a new prime minister, and I guarantee we'll get one
in the next 18 months, probably much sooner,
I am trying to force these guys to give us something
for the working class, for living standards.
And
I don't have millionaire funders behind me.
All I have is your support, the support of the public.
So you get out there,
get in touch with your politicians, and say,
"Listen, why are you not doing anything on inequality?
Why are you not doing anything on living standards
and tax of the rich specifically?" And listen,
I don't know if we're going to get it.
I don't know if we're going to get movement from Labour.
I don't know if the Greens are ever going to be
in a situation where they can really win the election.
But I tell you this right now,
I'd bet any money on it, if Farage and Reform win,
it is not going to improve your living standards.
I'll bet any money on that.
And I'm not often wrong.
And my last thing I've got here, number nine,
is just one word which says hope.
Listen, we have a common interest here.
We have a common interest here, okay?
What is happening right now is hurting living standards
for 60, 70, 80, 85% of the public.
And I know there's a lot we disagree on.
There's an awful lot we disagree on.
But we need to find the space to agree on one thing,
which is this growth in inequality is unacceptable, and
we need to force our politicians to take action on that.
I'm going to be out there
lobbying ******* hard the teams of Burnham and Rayner
and Streeting and Miliband.
And really,
the only power I've got behind me is the fact
that millions of you guys watch my videos every week.
This is a crucial moment right now.
We have a chance.
We have a chance to change the policy of this country,
and I need you to back me.
And in the last, like, year or so,
I've been all over the world, and
there's people doing this everywhere.
I'm so impressed by the work
that Gabriel Zucman's been doing in France.
I've been impressed by what we've seen in the US,
in New York with Mamdani.
These are guys who,
they're not just sending out messages.
They're working ******* hard to do it,
to do it, to plan the taxes, to get it right.
And we need to bring these people together.
We need to bring these people together.
But the opportunity is there.
The people want it.
And I think the only thing that's really stopping us
from getting these things is that we are being convinced
to fight against each other and to hate each other,
and we need to be able to move past that.
And look, I'm kind of knackered.
It's been a lot.
Like, with this change in,
the leadership and the upcoming new prime minister,
I, just like everyone, I'm sort of desperately
running around trying to get my piece of influence.
And I don't have to do it,
but I do it anyway, because I think we can win.
I think we can win.
And if enough of you support me and push like I'm doing,
then we will win.
All right.
Thank you.
Good luck.
Tax wealth, not work.